<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The act of classis for purging the iudicatories and other places of publick trust.</title>
            <title>Laws, etc.</title>
            <author>Scotland.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 25 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92497</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S1116A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R183916</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45097934</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45097934</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171510</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92497)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171510)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2576:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The act of classis for purging the iudicatories and other places of publick trust.</title>
                  <title>Laws, etc.</title>
                  <author>Scotland.</author>
                  <author>Scotland. Convention of Estates.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Evan Tyler,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Sutro Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland --  Politics and government --  1625-1649.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Officials and employees --  Discipline.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:171510:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:171510:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The ACT of <hi>CLASSIS</hi> for purging the IUDICATORIES and other places of publick Truſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T <hi>Edinburgh</hi> the twenty third day of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary</hi> 1649. years. The Eſtates of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament preſently conveened, in this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Seſsion of the ſecond Trienniall Parliament, By vertue of an Act of the Committee or Eſtates, who had power and authority from the laſt Parliament for conveening the Parliament; Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering, That forſameikle as the late Committee of Eſtates, did in the indicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Parliament by their Act of the 27. of <hi>October</hi> laſt, declare and warn, as after follows, To wit, That whereas the corruption of Judicatories of this Kingdom and Officers of Eſtate, and others per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in publick truſt, have been the cauſe and fountain from whence our former evil hath proceeded. And whereas by our Solemn Acknowledgment agreed upon by Church and State, We are bound to God, by our Engagement to <hi>England</hi> we are bound to them, and by the forecited and publict Declaration, we are obliged before the World, to indeavour the purgation and reformation of our Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories and places of publick truſt: And foraſmuch as the foreſaids Perſons, and all who are in publick truſt are liable to the judgement and cenſure of Parliament for their procedure in their ſeverall places and Offices: Likeas by the Agreement at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> and <hi>Striviling</hi> all ſuch as have been imployed in publick place and truſt, and have been acceſſory to the late unlawfull Engagement ſhould forbear the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of their places in the mean time; and all Queſtions are referred to the Determination of the Parliament: And whereas by the ſaid Treaty, all theſe who have been acceſſory to the ſaid Engagement are challengeable for their ſaid acceſsion, at the leaſt in ſo far as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns their places and publick truſt, and the debarring of them from any of theſe. Therefore the Committee of Eſtates doth hereby warne and cite all and every one of theſe who exerciſed any office, place, or publick truſt, or who were Members, or Clerks of any pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Iudicatories, of whatſoever degree, quality, or condition ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, in Burgh or Land within this Kingdom, and hath been acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſory to the late Engagement, or are guilty of the faults mentioned in the Printed Acts of the twenty two of <hi>September,</hi> and fourth of <hi>October,</hi> To compeir before the Eſtates of Parliament at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> the 4. day of <hi>Ianuary</hi> next to come in a peaceable way, accompanied
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:171510:3"/>onely with their own domeſtick Servants, to hear and ſee the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament take ſuch courſe, as they in their Iuſtice and Wiſdom for the good of the Kingdom ſhall think fit, for purging of the Judicatories, and for declaring their places vacand, and filling them with ſuch as are able and qualified perſons, fitteſt for the ſervice, and may give moſt contentment, and as have continued conſtant in the Covenant and Cauſe in the time of tryall, And for debarring them (who are put out) from any other publick places, or truſt, during ſuch time, and in ſuch manner, as the Eſtates of Parliament ſhall think fit, With certification to every one of the perſons concerned as is aboveſaid, and warned by this publick Proclamation, (which the Committee of Eſtates declares, That they finde it a ſufficient intimation in this noture caſe of ſo great and publick a back-ſliding to all perſons con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned therein for the effect foreſaid, to be eſteemed by them equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent to a perſonall citation, or at their dwelling houſe upon parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular ſummonds againſt every one of them) to compeir before the Eſtates of Parliament as is before ſaid and compeir not, That then the Eſtates will proceed both to determine the generall queſtion and the particular concerning their places and truſt, and take what farther courſe, they ſhall think fitting for the good of the Kingdom: And forſameikle, as the Eſtates of Parliament being now conveened have ratified the foreſaid Act in all the heads thereof, and by open Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation intimate the fame. Likeas they have made their ſolemn Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of the publick ſins and beraches of the Covenant, and their Solemn Ingagement to all the duties contained therein, namely theſe which do in a more ſpeciall way relate to the dangers of theſe times; And in relation thereto have renewed their Solemn League and Covenant before God: And by their Act of the 16. of <hi>Ianuary</hi> inſtant, have diſclaimed and condemned the late unlawfull Engagement, as contrary to GODS Word, and a manifeſt breach of Covenant and Treaties, as deſtructive to the Cauſe and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, to Religion, the King and theſe Kingdoms: And is the cauſe of all the oppreſsions and miſeries that hath followed or may follow thereupon: And therefore, and for many other reaſons, Have annul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and repealed all Acts made by the late Parliament and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Eſtates in proſecution thereof, and have ratified and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proven the Proteſtation in Parliament and oppoſition made thereof by this Kingdom againſt the Authors and Abettors thereafter, and the late Treaty made at <hi>Stirling,</hi> debarring all acceſſory to that unlawful Engagement from the exerciſe of their places or publick truſt, untill the meeting &amp; determination of this preſent Parliament, unto whom all Civill queſtions are referred: And likewiſe hath confirmed the aſſurance given by the Committee unto the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> that we ſhould not admit any of theſe authors or abettors of the late En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement to any publick place or truſt without the conſent of that Kingdom againſt w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> their Engagement was, as is more fully expreſt in their Anſwer of the 6. of <hi>October</hi> laſt. And whereas the Eſtates of Parliament, are not only ſatisfied of the truth, lawfulneſs and neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:171510:3"/>of the foreſaid grounds, but alſo are convinced in their conſciences from the Word of God, from the large Treaty between the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and from their Oath of Parliament, from their ſolemn League and Covenant, eſpecially from the 2.4. and 5. Articles thereof, and from ſad and dear-bought experience, That the Malignant dealing of ſome, and the profane looſe walking of others who have been Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Iudicatories, and imployed in places of power and publick truſt hath been a chief cauſe of all the evils both of ſin and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment under which the Land now groans; And that the Lord requires in his Word, that thoſe who judge and bear charge among his people ſhould not only be able men, but ſuch as fear God, hate covetouſneſs, and deal truly. And that it is of ſpeciall importance for the remedie of all our evils, and for ſecuring and advancing of Religion &amp; Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, for keeping a right underſtanding between the Kingdoms, and for proſecuting all the ends of the ſolemn League &amp; Covenant, and for removing the judgement of God and preventing or diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing all the deſigns and oppoſition of enemies of all ſorts, and for procuting the bleſsing of God upon the whole Land, That men not only of known ability, but alſo of approven integrity and conſtant af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to the Cauſe and good and Chriſtian converſation, be intruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in all Iudicatories and places of power and truſt, according to the ſeventh deſire of the Commiſsioners of the Church given in to the laſt Parliament, as ſo abſolutely neceſſary for the ſecuring of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which by the Ingagers themſelves in the Treaty at <hi>Stirling</hi> is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Church their determination. Which determination anent the qualifications aforeſaids is clearly ſet down in the 5.6.7.10. and 12. pages of the Acknowledgement and their Declaration emitted to the world.</p>
            <p>Therefore the Eſtates of Parliament remembering well the Laud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able precedents of the Parliaments, 1641 and 1646 and ſeverall others for purgation of the Judecatories and places of truſt; And conſidering that all perſons both by the common Law, by many Acts of Parliament, and the nature of their place and truſt, are compt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able for their proceedings in their ſeverall places and truſt, which they have <hi>ad vitam aut culpam:</hi> And pondering how great a fault it is to have had any hand or acceſſion in the Inacting, or inforcing, or proſecuting ſo unlawfull an Engagement, thereby drawing on the Land (ſo far as they could) the wrath of God and all the miſeries of a War with our Brethren of <hi>England,</hi> againſt Covenant, Treaties, and many warnings from the Kirk, and contrary to the Petitions from many Synods, Presbyteries and Shires, and the ſolemn Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations of ſo great a number of each Eſtate in Parliament: They do in perſuance of their ſolemn Acknowledgement, performance of their vows to God, Declaration emitted to the World, and aſſurance given to the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> both in the large Treaty, 1641. and late Anſwer 6. of <hi>October</hi> laſt, and for ſatisfying of the Kirks juſt deſires for Purgation and Reformation of our Judicatories, and for determination of this queſtion anent places of truſt, referred by the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:171510:4"/>Treaty at <hi>Sterling</hi> to their determination, and for deterring all others in this or ſubſequent generation, who ſhall be intruſted with publick power or place from drawing on this nation the guiltleſſe and miſery of inoffenſive, unneceſſary &amp; unlawful war, and againſt Covenant and Treaties, and publick warnings from Church Judicatories and Shires, and for incouraging all who ſhal be in publick place or truſt in times of new ſtraits and trialls; To abide conſtantly by the Cauſe and Covenant, and to give evident teſtimonies thereunto againſt all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and apoſtacie. The Eſtates of Parliament upon this and many other great and weighty conſiderations moving and preſſing them to this neceſſary dutie, Do therefore Declare Inact and Ordain, that all theſe Officers of Eſtate, Members or Clerks of the Parliament, Committees thereof, ſecret Counſell, Seſſion, Exchequer, Juſtice Courts, Commiſſion for plantation of Kirks, or conſervation of the Peace, Sherif Courts, Stewart Courts, Baillie Courts, Commiſſar Courts, Bailies of Regalitie Courts, Warden Courts, of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Mint-houſe, Admirall Court, Gild Court, Town Counſell, or any other publick Judicatorie, or Deacons of Crafts, and all who had any office, place, or publick truſt, and all having deputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from, or dependance upon any of theſe aforeſaid, who were guilty of any of the faults contained in the four ſeverall Claſſes after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, ſhall be removed and ſecluded from publick truſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſeverall rules <hi>reſpective</hi> after following.</p>
            <div n="1" type="class">
               <head>The firſt Claſſe.</head>
               <p>The Eſtates declare all theſe to be comprehended in the firſt Claſſe, who were generall Officers, which led and accompanied the Army into <hi>England;</hi> And all thoſe Officers that continued in the Engagement, who commanded the Forces at <hi>Mauchlin moore,</hi> or at <hi>Striviling,</hi> and all thoſe who were principally active in perſwading, or bringing over of the Forces from <hi>Ireland,</hi> and all theſe perſons who were plotters, chief actors and prime promoters of the late un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull Engagement from the beginning to the end thereof, in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, Committees, or otherwayes: And ſiclike all theſe who were chief actors and prime promoters of the horrid Rebellion of <hi>James Grahame,</hi> and who ſince have either accepted of charge or joyned as volunteers in the ſaid unlawfull Engagement, or taken the Oath in Committees, or Subſcribed the bond for themſelves or others for the Engagement, or ſate in the Committees or other meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and gave order for proſecuting the ſaid Engagement, or who otherwayes gave or received, and execute orders againſt others for proſecuting the Engagement; As alſo ſuch Clerks of Parliament, Committees thereof, ſecret Councell or Seſſion, who were guiltie of any of the Faults contained in any of the Claſſe at St. <hi>Andrews,</hi> and retaining their former Principles of Malignancie, and have been Active in their places or imployments for promoving the late unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Engagement.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="class">
               <head>The ſecond Claſſe.</head>
               <p>The Eſtates alſo Declare all theſe to be comprehended in the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:171510:4"/>ſecond Claſſe, who not being included in the firſt Claſſe, have been formerly Claſſed or Cenſured for Malignancie, or guilty of the crimes contained in the firſt and ſecond Claſſe at St. <hi>Andrews,</hi> of the date at St. <hi>Andrews</hi> the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſix hundred and <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> years; And ſince have either accepted of charge or joyned as voluntiers in the ſaid unlawfull En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, or taken the Oath in Committees, or ſubſcribed the bond for themſelves or others for the Engagement, or ſat in Committees or other meetings, and gave order for proſecuting the ſaid En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, or who otherwayes gave or received and execute Orders againſt others for proſecuting the Engagement; And ſiclike all thoſe perſons, although not formerly Claſſed, and not being included in the firſt Claſſe, who were Officers which were upon any of the expeditions into <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Scotland</hi> for the ſaid Engagement; And ſiclike all theſe who concurred in Petitions, Proteſtations, Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrances or letters for moving of the Parliament or Committees to carrie on the Engagement; And ſiclike all theſe who proteſt againſt the cauſe of the Faſt, or the Kirks Declarations, or Petitions of the Presbyteries or Kirk ſeſſions againſt the Engagement, or read, or cauſed read at Kirk doors the Committees Obſervations againſt the Aſſemblies Declaration, or interrupted Divine Service, or Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates and perſons of qualitie, or who removed at the reading of the Aſſemblies Declaration; Siclike all theſe who not onely took the Oath injoyned by the laſt Parliament for the Engagement in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees, or ſubſcribed the band, or Declared themſelves ready to do the ſame, but alſo ſecluded others, or proteſt againſt others for their not taking of the Oath, or not ſubſcribing of the Band; Siclike all theſe who injoyned and preſſed others to ſubſcribe the Band, or take the Oath for carring on the Engagement; And ſiclike all theſe who concurred as Members or Clerks in Acts of Parliament and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Eſtates for proſecuting the ſaid Engagement, or for preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing others thereunto, and ſuch who conſulted and gave advice for penning or proſecuting of the proceſs againſt the honeſt Miniſters who were at <hi>Mauchlin moore,</hi> or any others for their oppoſing or not joyning in the Engagement.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="class">
               <head>The third Claſſe.</head>
               <p>The Eſtates likewiſe Declares all theſe to be comprehended in the the third Claſſe (who not being included in the firſt or ſecond Claſs) ſat in Parliament and Committee of Eſtates, and took the Oaths foreſaid for the Engagement, or ſat as Clerks in any of theſe or any other Judicatories, and gave no publick teſtimonie againſt the ſaid Engagement, carried on therein by their ſervice, or were any way known to have been for the ſame in their judgement manifeſted by their expreſſions and actions; Siclike all theſe perſons who have taken the Oath foreſaid, or ſubſcribed the Band for the Engagement, or who in Committees of war or other meetings, Town Counſel or other Courts, have refuſed or oppoſed the deſires of any Petitions from Shires, Presbyteries, Seſſions or other Kirk Iudicatories
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:171510:5"/>againſt the Engagement, or concurred in Acts to force the Diſſenters, Petitioners or others to concur in the firſt or ſecond leavies, or other acceſſion to the ſaid Engagement, or with the Forces under the Earl of <hi>Crauford,</hi> Earl of <hi>Lanerick</hi> and <hi>George Monro;</hi> And ſiclike all ſuch who were either forcers, urgers or ſeducers of others to concur in the ſaid Engagement, or with the foreſaid forces: And ſiclike all theſe who accept Commiſſions to be Officers, or joyned as voluntiers to the forces under the Duke of <hi>Hamilton</hi> or the Earls of <hi>Crauford, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerick</hi> or <hi>George Monro,</hi> Likeas all perſons who in their ſpeeches and actions did evidence their judgements for, and affection to that ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full courſe, Or who (in ſuch a time of triall) after ſuch Petitions from the Shires, and ſuch Declarations and warnings from the Church, evidencing to all the unlawfulneſſe of the Engagement againſt Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant and Treatie) did not give any countenance to the cauſe or teſtimony of their judgement and affection againſt ſuch a defection and dangerous War, when, and where they had the opportunitie to do it with others.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="class">
               <head>The fourth Claſſe.</head>
               <p>The Eſtates of Parliament in like manner Declares all theſe to be comprehended in the fourth Claſſe, who being Members of Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, Clerks and perſons in publick truſt as aforeſaid, are given to uncleanneſſe, bribery, ſwearing, drunkenneſſe, or deceiving, or are otherwayes openly profane, and groſly ſcandulous in their converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or who neglect the Worſhip of God in their families.</p>
               <p>The Eſtates Declares, Enacts and Ordains, That all ſuch Officers of Eſtate, Members of any Judicatory, Clerks and others before mentioned, and all perſons in publick place or truſt, who are guilty of any of the faults before ſpecified, contained in any of the four Claſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes before ſet down, be preſently removed by this Parliament, or ſuch Committees or perſons as ſhall be by them authoriſed with power to that effect) from their preſent places and Offices, and all other publick truſt mentioned in the Act of Claſſe at St. <hi>Andrews</hi> or which hes deputation from, or dependance, upon the forenamed Judicato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries or Officers (without prejudice of the ſubſcription of them, in the mean time for the exerciſe of their places, conform to the Treaty and former Acts of Committee ratified in Parliament) And that theſe places belonging to them, <hi>ad vitam vel culpam</hi> be declared va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant, and filled with other perſons, who are known to be free of theſe faults, and not onely to have ſufficient ability, but alſo who have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven reall proof of their conſtant affection to the Cauſe, and a good converlation; and that theſe who hereupon ſhall be removed from their places and offices, are hereby diſcharged from medling there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after in any excerciſe, badge or benefit thereof, under the pain of confiſcation of their movables, life rent of their eſtates, impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their perſons, and of being declared for ever uncapable of the meaneſt publick truſt within the Kingdom; Likeas the Eſtates of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, upon the manifold grounds aforeſaid, doth Declare, Enact, and Ordain, That none of theſe perſons who are guilty of any of the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:171510:5"/>crimes contained in the firſt Claſſe, ſhall ever be capable of, or admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to any publick office, place or truſt aforementioned within this Kingdom during all the dayes of their lifetimes; Likeas they Declare, Enact and Ordain, That none of theſe who are guiltie of any of the crimes mentioned in the ſecond Claſſe, ſhall be capable, of or admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to any publick office, place or truſt aforementioned within this Kingdom for ten years to come. And farther, untill they have given ſufficient evidence of their change of their Malignant principles and practices, and of their firm reſolution and affection to promove the Ends of the Covenant in all times of ſubſequent triall (whereof the Judicatories of the Church and State <hi>reſpective</hi> having power for that effect are to judge impartially, as in GODS ſight) And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by have given ſatisfaction to the Kirk and to both Kingdoms ſo far wrought by them, according to the aſſurance given on the ſixt of <hi>October</hi> laſt.</p>
               <p>Likeas the Eſtates Declare, Enacts and Ordains, That no perſon who is guilty of any of the faults contained in the third Claſſe (excepting theſe as are after excepted) ſhall be capableof, or admtted to any publick place, office or truſt aforementioned with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this Kingdom during five years to come, and farther, untill they have given ſufficient evidence of their change of their Malignant principles and practices, and of their firm reſolution and affection to promove the Ends of the Covenant in all times of ſubſequent triall (whereof the Iudicatories of Church and State <hi>reſpective</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving power or that effect, are to judge impartially as in the ſight of GOD) And thereby have given ſatisfaction to the Kirk and both Kingdoms ſo far wronged by them according to the aſſurance given on the ſixth of <hi>October</hi> laſt.</p>
               <p>Excepting theſe who before the time of the promoving of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement were known to have been honeſt in the Cauſe of God, and not Malignant, and who were known by their carriage to have been againſt the Engagement in their judgement, and did concur in Petitioning, diſſenting, proteſting, or riſing in Armes or other wayes did bear teſtimony againſt it, as they had opportunity, and who not knowing the nature and drift of the Band or Oath for the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, were deceived and enſnared to the ſubſcribing or taking of the ſame, which perſons having the foreſaid qualifications, and giving ſatisfaction to the Kirk, are remitted to the next Seſsion of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, at which time according to their Repentance and carriage, they may be declared capable of publick places and truſt (ſo far as the Parliament ſhall think them fit.)</p>
               <p>Likeas the Eſtates Declares, Enacts and Ordains, That no perſon guilty of any of the faults contained in the fourth Claſſe, ſhall be capable of, or admitted to any publick place or truſt aforementioned within this Kingdom for a yeer to come; And farther, untill they have given to the Iudicatories of Church and State, <hi>reſpective,</hi> ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient evidence of their change of their profane and ſcandalous life,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:171510:6"/>and of their firm reſolution and conſtant endeavour for a good and Chriſtian converſation (whereof the Iudicatories of the Church and State ſhall judge impartially as in Gods ſight) And this without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation to the former Laws made againſt the ſame.</p>
               <p>Likeas it is hereby declared, That where any perſons are excluded by the former Claſſe from the exerciſe of their Heretable Offices, That during the time of their ſecluſion, theſe places ſhall be ſupplied by ſuch Deputes, as the Parliament, Committee of Eſtates, or others Authorized by Parliament ſhall appoint to ſerve therein for the interim.</p>
               <p>It is always hereby declared, That this preſent Act ſhall not be extended to theſe Minors who being guilty of any of the faults a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, ſhall within three moneths after the publication hereof, if they be within the Kingdom, and if they be without the Kingdom, within the ſame ſpace after their return to the Countrey, Give ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient evidence to the Iudicatories of Church and State <hi>reſpective,</hi> having power for that effect of their Repentance, and of the change of their Malignant principles and practiſes, and of their firm reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution and endeavour to promove the Ends of the Covenant in all times of ſubſequent tryalls, and ſhall behave themſelves accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly unto their majority, and who within ſix moneths after their their majority ſhall ratifie the ſame.</p>
               <p>It is Declared, That this Act is without prejudice, to what far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cenſure the Eſtates ſhall think fit to inflict upon theſe who are guilty of the faults aforeſaid, and hath not by their due acceptance the benefit of the Treaty at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> and <hi>Stirling.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſaids Eſtates Declares, That they reſerve to themſelves, the conſideration of ſuch perſons as may fall under the exception of the third Claſſe, and what ſhall be done concerning them in the Committees of War of the ſeverall Shires when the Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees ſhall be nominate: And the ſaids Eſtates Ordains the Act foreſaid to be Publiſhed at the Mercat Croſſe of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> by an Herald, having diſplayed Armes by ſound of Trumpet, And thereafter Ordains the ſame to be Printed.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>William Scot,</hi> Cler. Parl.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
